<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>The Agavi Cookbook</title>

  <chapter>
    <title>Best Practices</title>

    <section>
      <title>Separating Business and Presentation Logic</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Sharing and Passing Around Data Inside Your Application</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Decorators and Slots</title>

      <para>why decorate, setting up slots, passing around data between
      slots</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Popular Recipes</title>

    <section>
      <title>Removing the "index.php" Part From URLs</title>

      <para>You need mod_rewrite (or something similar for other web servers,
      such as ISAPI_Rewrite for Microsoft IIS) to get rid of the "index.php"
      part in incoming and generated URLs. Make sure mod_rewrite is enabled,
      and create a <filename>.htaccess</filename> file in your
      <filename>pub</filename> directory with the following contents:</para>

      <para><programlisting># enable rewrite engine
RewriteEngine On

RewriteBase /~dzuelke/_projects/agavi/trunk/samples/pub/
# e.g. RewriteBase /~dzuelke/_projects/agavi/trunk/samples/pub/
# usually just "/" if your application's pub dir is the document root

# if requested url does not exist (i.e. it's likely an agavi route), pass it as path info to index.php
RewriteRule ^$ index.php/ [QSA,L]
RewriteCond %{REQUEST_FILENAME} !-f
RewriteCond %{REQUEST_FILENAME} !-d
RewriteRule (.*) index.php/$1 [QSA,L]</programlisting></para>

      <important>
        <para>If you are running Apache with PHP as CGI, you cannot rewrite to
        a PHP file and pass path info. In this case, we have to resort to a
        query parameter to pass the incoming path to Agavi. To do that, change
        the two rewrite rules to:</para>

        <para><programlisting>RewriteRule ^$ index.php?something=/ [QSA,L]</programlisting>and</para>

        <para><programlisting>RewriteRule (.*) index.php?something=/$1 [QSA,L]</programlisting>Then,
        tell the WebRouting that you're using this rewrite method in
        <filename>factories.xml</filename>:</para>

        <para><programlisting>&lt;routing class="AgaviWebRouting"&gt;
  &lt;parameters&gt;
    &lt;parameter name="path_info_parameter"&gt;something&lt;/parameter&gt;
  &lt;/parameters&gt;
&lt;/routing&gt;</programlisting>Of course, you are free to use whatever you
        prefer as the parameter name. It will not be set as a Request
        parameter, unless the user actually supplies a parameter with this
        name.</para>
      </important>

      <para>The important thing is that you use the
      <emphasis>external</emphasis> path to the <filename>pub</filename>
      directory as the RewriteBase, i.e. the path that you would have to enter
      in your web browser location bar to reach the index page. If the
      <filename>pub</filename> directory is the document root, then the
      RewriteBase is just <filename>/</filename>.</para>

      <para>The RewriteCond is a condition that executes the following
      RewriteRule if the requested filename (that is the incoming URL already
      mapped to a filesystem name by Apache) does <emphasis>not</emphasis>
      exist. If the requested URL exists, for instance, when an image on the
      webserver is requested, Agavi won't be called. Otherwise, the framework
      is started and the given URL is handed to Agavi as so-called Path Info
      which the WebRouting will use to match a route.</para>

      <para>If you use ISAPI_Rewrite or another plugin for IIS, you can't use
      the rewrite condition shown above since it's not supported. Instead, you
      should create a RewriteCond that checks if the incoming URL does not
      fall into a certain schema (e.g. doesn't begin with
      <filename>/images</filename> and <filename>/css</filename> so these
      don't get rewritten and handed to Agavi).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Serving "application/xhtml+xml" to capable browsers</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Propel Integration</title>

      <para>simple</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Cookie-Based Auto-Login</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Redirecting back to the originally requested page after
      login</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Serving Output Variants of the Same Content</title>

      <para>a quick example using a LatestProductsAction or whatever</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>In-Depth Tutorials</title>

    <section>
      <title>Populating and Validating Forms</title>

      <para>explain the FormPopulationFilter</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Caching</title>

      <para>document the execution filter here, with examples, explanation of
      how decorators are cached or not and slots can be included, variable
      caching, groups, request methods, cache lifetime</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Routing Examples</title>

      <para></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Adding an XMLRPC or Other Interface to Your Web
      Application</title>

      <para>walk people through the basic steps/ideas</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>