<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>An Introduction to Agavi</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para>Agavi is a Web Application Framework for PHP 5. While it lies in the
    nature of a framework to simplify the application development process,
    Agavi won't do that at any cost. The primary goals are flexibility,
    cleanliness and structure. You won't find HTML Form helper methods in
    Agavi (because they aren't necessary, we have something better, more on
    that later), and we use XML configuration files because we believe that
    they offer better structuring abilites than alternatives such as YAML. If
    you're looking for a solution that assists you in serious high-end
    development, that has smart and innovative solutions to common problems
    that haven't been solved properly before, and that encourages and enforces
    a clean development process to ensure your code remains maintainable and
    extensible, you've come to the right place.</para>
  </preface>

  <chapter>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <section>
      <title>Elements of an Application</title>

      <para>Every Agavi Application consists of one or more Modules. Modules
      are a means of structuring an application, and offer various
      configuration and control abilities, such as per-module autoloading,
      dedicated filters, bundled models and more.</para>

      <para>Each Module contains one or more Actions. Actions contain logic
      code and are totally independent of the way you're using them, be it
      through a normal web application, or via a SOAP interface - the code
      remains exactly the same, you usually never touch them again once they
      are finished. If you're wondering what role Actions play in the MVC
      pattern, the most accurate explanation would likely be that they are a
      bridge between Controller and Model, but a lot closer to the Controller
      than to the Model - think of Actions as parts of the Controller which
      are loaded on demand.</para>

      <para>Once an Action finished execution, control is passed to the View,
      which handles all presentational aspects of the Action that was
      executed, like redirection, forwarding to other Actions, HTTP headers,
      the layout and Templates to use, Cookies and so on. This separation
      reduces a lot of redundant code and guarantees maximum flexibility of
      your business logic - as aforementioned, it's simply a matter of
      throwing in a new Template if you want an existing Action to output,
      say, JSON in addition to plain HTML.</para>

      <para>Models encapsulate business logic transactions and offer a fully
      transparent API to the Actions that use it, thereby allowing you to
      change the underlying implementation without having to adjust any other
      code. The more logic you put into Models, the fewer lines you have to
      write in your Actions, and you get the benefit of universal code
      reusability - not only within your application! While Models may be
      bundled with a Module, they can also be "global" to your application,
      and you may, of course, share Models across applications. You don't even
      have to re-implement existing code - if you already have classes that
      serve as models, you can use them as Models with Agavi, too.</para>

      <para>Last but not least, there's a whole bunch of configuration files
      (of which only three are mandatory!) that allow you to configure all
      aspects of the Framework. You may even have different configuration
      settings per Environment and Context (see <xref
      endterm="environmentsandcontexts-title"
      linkend="environmentsandcontexts" />) for maximum flexibility and
      convenience. Also, it's easy to centralize single parts or complete
      chunks of configuration files, or you can offer smart presets for your
      applications, by referencing other configuration files and using them as
      "parents" from within your application configuration files. This cascade
      of configuration files that are used is not limited in length, so you
      can have multiple levels of global definitions for your applications if
      you like. For example, the default <filename>autoload.xml</filename>
      uses Agavi's own autoloading definitions as the parent, making upgrades
      totally painless because your application's
      <filename>autoload.xml</filename> contains only your own
      declarations.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="environmentsandcontexts">
      <title id="environmentsandcontexts-title">Environments and
      Contexts</title>

      <para>The framework is started by bootstrapping an environment. Typical
      environments would be "development", "testing" or "production". You may
      configure any number of environments, but only one of them is used
      during execution.</para>

      <para>Environments allow for extremely fine-grained settings for each
      machine an application is running on. The various Environments may have
      different database configurations, logging settings and levels, debug
      settings and even filters or factories. Also, each developer in a team
      may have his own Environment for development, with his or her own
      database settings etc. which eliminates the need for people constantly
      having to change their settings, accidentally committing changed files
      to SCM repositories or missing changes because configuration files were
      set to <emphasis>ignore</emphasis>.</para>

      <para>A Context encapsulates a running instance of the framework. While
      any aspect of the framework, even system settings and autoloads may be
      configured per Environment, you're a bit more restricted in Context
      configuration, and that's intentional. A Context's job is to hold the
      proper implementations that are needed to execute the application in the
      current <emphasis>context</emphasis> (therefore the name), such as "web"
      for normal requests to an application through a browser, "xmlrpc" for an
      XMLRPC interface of an application, or "console" for a Context that
      exposes the application to the command line.</para>

      <para>All configuration files support the configuration per Environment
      and Context (if applicable) without any performance disadvantage - Agavi
      compiles them into highly optimized variants for each Environment and
      Context when needed for minimum overhead.</para>

      <section>
        <title>A Closer Look at Context Initialization</title>

        <para>Agavi's context class (AgaviContext) is initialized according to
        settings defined in <filename>factories.xml</filename>. Normally you
        don't have to worry about how it is done but if you decide to
        specialize some of the Agavi's core classes the order of
        initialization might become important.</para>

        <para>Agavi's core classes are initialized in the following order by
        default:<orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>DatabaseManager</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>SessionStorage</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>ValidatorManager</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>User</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>LoggerManager</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Controller</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Request</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Routing</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>This means that for example a User implementation
        cannot use <classname>LoggerManager</classname> in its
        <function>initialize</function> method. The initialization order of
        these framework core classes is defined in
        <classname>AgaviFactoryConfigHandler</classname> and it cannot be
        changed.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How a Request is Processed</title>

      <para>If you call an URL that is handled by pub/index.php, Agavi will
      bootstrap the specified (or default) Environment and then create an
      instance of the specified (or default) Context (this instantiation sets
      up all of the core components of the framework). Finally, the request is
      dispatched from the Context's Controller instance.</para>

      <para>The dispatch method first executes the routing (if enabled) to
      determine the Module/Action that are to be executed. Then, a filter
      chain containing all Global Filters is created, and the DispatchFilter
      is added to that chain as the last element. Each filter will be called
      in nested sequence, with the last filter being the DispatchFilter, which
      calls the first forward to the requested Module and Action. After that,
      the control passes back through the filters to the dispatch method,
      which sends the Response contents and exits. Filters are given the
      global Response as a parameter to work with, so they can modify content,
      send Cookies and so on.</para>

      <para>When a forward happens, Agavi does some checks to determine if the
      requested Module/Action exists, if the Module the Action belongs to is
      enabled and so on. Then, a filter chain is created, with the first
      filter being the Security Filter if security is enabled. This filter
      will forward unauthenticated users to the default "Login Action" if a
      requested Action requires authentication, and also prevent access of
      Actions an user doesn't have sufficient credentials for by forwarding to
      the default "Secure Action". After that, the Action Filters are added to
      the chain, followed by the Action Filters defined by the Action's
      Module. The last filter in the chain is the Execution Filter, usually
      either AgaviExecutionFilter or AgaviCachingExecutionFilter. Again, each
      filter in the chain is called and may do modifications to the Response
      instance, which is a new one for each Action that is processed and will
      be merged to the global Response by the Controller once control returns
      to the forward method.</para>

      <para>The Execution Filter, once reached, will handle Validation, run
      the Action (or skip execution if the Action doesn't serve the Request
      method), determine the View to execute and then execute the View and,
      after that, start the rendering of the output.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>