<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<book>
  <title>Agavi Migration Guide</title>

  <bookinfo>
    <releaseinfo>$Id$</releaseinfo>
  </bookinfo>

  <chapter>
    <title>Migrating from Agavi 0.10 to 0.11</title>

    <section>
      <title>Migrating from Agavi 0.10 to 0.11</title>

      <para>Migrating from Agavi 0.10 is unfortunately quite a lot of work
      because of the more-or-less complete overhaul of the framework.</para>

      <para>The easiest way to get started is to create a completely new
      project with the <filename>agavi</filename> script and start moving
      modules and actions one by one, copying the execute method from the old
      action to the new one, testing if it works and fix whatever
      breaks.</para>

      <para>A few pointers to help on the way:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Parameters set with <literal>$this-&gt;setAttribute('foo',
          'bar')</literal> in the action's execute-method are now directly
          available in the template. You no longer need to manually set the
          template attributes in the view.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Read up on the new templating system (<link
          linkend="???">http://groups.google.com/group/agavi-users/browse_thread/thread/6e1a1033b4b8b77c</link>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Routing, the request object, the controller, user, translation
          manager and the request data are now available directly in the
          templates via <literal>$ro</literal>, <literal>$rq</literal>,
          <literal>$ct</literal>, <literal>$us</literal>,
          <literal>$tm</literal> and <literal>$rd</literal> , no need to pass
          these objects to the view. The name of the variables is configurabe
          through <literal>output_types.xml</literal></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>Action::getRequestMethod()</literal> is deprecated.
          Actions now have <literal>executeRead()</literal> and
          <literal>executeWrite()</literal> that handle HTTP GET and HTTP POST
          respectively. If you really need, you can also use a plain
          <literal>execute()</literal> which would handle both GET and
          POST.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para><literal>$this-&gt;getContext()-&gt;getRequest()-&gt;getParameter()</literal>
          is no longer needed. The action's execute -method takes an
          <literal>AgaviRequestDataHolder</literal> -object as it's parameter
          and the request parameters are available via that object's
          <literal>getParameter</literal>-method.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Actions no longer return attributes of the View-class
          (<literal>r<literal>eturn View::SUCCESS</literal></literal>), but
          strings. For an action that wants to indicate it was successful, you
          would return the string "Success".</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Views do not need to set the template file manually anymore.
          The view makes an educated guess as to the filename
          (<literal>&lt;Name&gt;&lt;ReturnValueFromAction&gt;.php</literal>).
          For example, if <literal>IndexAction</literal> returns 'Success',
          <literal>IndexSuccessView</literal> would use the template
          <filename>IndexSuccess.php</filename>.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Application config variables are now available via
          <literal>AgaviConfig::get()</literal>. For instance, the modpub
          -directory would be
          <literal>AgaviConfig::get('core.modpub')</literal>. No need for
          constants anymore (<literal>AG_MOD_PUB</literal>)</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Views now have multiple execute-methods (eg executeHtml,
          executeRss, executeXml etc), agavi chooses which one to run based on
          the output type. This means one view can handle HTML, RSS, XML and,
          say, PDF output at once, and will choose the proper template based
          on the configuration in output_types.xml. All you need to do is add
          a new execute-method to the view (and of course configure the output
          type in output_types.xml).</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold"> !!!! DO NOT USE THE PLAIN FALLBACK
          execute() METHOD IN THE VIEWS !!!!</emphasis></para>

          <para>This is simply because if you set the output type to, say, RSS
          but the view does not support it, you don't really want to display a
          HTML page or whatever, you probably want to throw an exception or
          something similar.</para>

          <para><emphasis role="bold">!!!! ALWAYS ALWAYS ALWAYS USE THE
          OUTPUT-TYPE BASED EXECUTE METHODS !!!!</emphasis></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Use the agavi build script to generate your actions, modules
          and so on. This can take advantage of code templates. Simply put a
          <filename>build.properties</filename> -file where your agavi-script
          resides and add the line<literal></literal></para>

          <para><programlisting>template.dir=${project.dir}/dev/code_templates</programlisting></para>

          <para>(write documentation about code templates)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>